Register of the Alonzo Englebert Taylor Papers, 1911-1943
Hoover Institution Archives
Alonzo Englebert Taylor Papers,
1911-1943
XX267
Taylor, Alonzo Englebert, 1871-1949
26 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 album box, 1 envelope (15 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, studies, bulletins, statistical data, and maps, relating to economic conditions and food supply in Europe during World War I, postwar reconstruction, and activities of the War Trade Board, Food Administration, and American Relief Administration
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
American Relief Administration.; United States. Food Administration.; United States. War Trade Board.; International relief.; Reconstruction (1914-1939)--Europe.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian Relief; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects; World War, 1914-1918--Food question; World War, 1914-1918--United States; Europe; United States--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Commerce
Biographical Note
1871 March 19 Born, Alden, Iowa
1886-1888 Student, Cornell College, Mount Vernon, Iowa
1888-1890 Attended DePauw University, Greencastle, Indiana
1890-1891, Attended University of Berlin, Germany
1894 M.D., University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
1899 Nov 2 Married Madeline Peck
1906 Author, Fermentation
1907 Doctor of Science?
1910 Professor, Pathology and Physiological Chemistry, University of California, Berkeley?
1910-1921 Rush Professor, Physiological Chemistry, University of Pennsylvania
1912 Author, Digestion and Metabolism
1917 Author (with V. L. Kellogg), The Food Problem
1917-1919 Member, American War Trade Board
1918 Author, War Bread
1920 LL.D., University of Wisconsin
1921-1936 Director, Food Research Institute, Stanford University
1928 Author (with Carl Lucas Alsberg), The Fats and Oils
1932 Author, Corn and Hog Surplus of the Corn Belt
1935 Author, The New Deal and Foreign Trade
1936-1940 Director of Research, General Mills, Inc., Minneapolis, Minnesota
1940- Consultant
1941 Author, Germany Then and Now
1949 Died
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1916-1941 (Box 1.)
  Correspondence, business cards, diary, identity passes, passports, schedule and miscellany relating to the life and work of Alonzo Taylor, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1943 (Box 1.-2.)
  Articles, remarks and speeches arranged chronologically by title
- Food Administration, 1917-1926 (Box 2.-13.)
  Agreements, articles, bulletins, charts and maps, clippings, correspondence, financial records, inventory, interview, issue of licenses for export and import of food to different parts of Europe, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, printed matter, remarks, reports, statements and telegrams relating to the allocation, exports and imports, requirements, production and deliveries of food to different countries of Europe during World War I, arranged by physical form. Includes the records of various departments of the United States Government, such as Council of National Defense, Export Administrative Board, State Department, War Industries Board, involved in the war time efforts to deal with distribution of food and related problems and postwar reconstruction in Europe
- War Trade Board, 1917-1919 (Box 14.-25.)
  Agreements, correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, organizational records, press release, printed matter, reports, statistical data sheets, survey, and telegrams relating to the activities of the War Trade Board, arranged by physical form
- Subject File, 1917-1920 (Box 26.)
  Applications, clippings, correspondence, financial records, memoranda, notes, reports and statistical records relating to the American relief efforts in Europe, arranged by physical form. Includes information relating to the economic situation in Germany, the effects of embargo and the conditions in German prison camps
- Oversize Materials, 1911-1918 (Box 27.-28.)
  Articles, clippings, correspondence, charts, conference proceedings, data sheets, maps, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes and telegrams relating to the domestic production, exports and imports of food in Denmark, the Netherlands, Norway and Switzerland, arranged alphabetically by the name of the country
- Photographs, 1921 (Photo File)
  1 album consisting of 12 prints depicting American relief activities in Poland following World War I, American Feast in Warsaw, Polish children's kitchens and schools, 1921; and 1 print depicting Alonzo Taylor, n.d.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1916-1941
  - Correspondence (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Diary (Folder 2)
  - Identity pass and business cards (Folder 3)
  - Passports (Folder 4)
  - Report (Folder 5)
  - Schedule (Folder 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 7)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1919-1943
  - "The Changing Food Supply", remarks, Forty Fourth Annual Conference, New Orleans, n.d. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Vienna, The Forsaken", The Saturday Evening Post, 1919 April 2. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "The Economic Consequences of the Peace", The Saturday Evening Post, 1920 September 25. Printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Credits for Export", The Saturday Evening Post, 1921 February 12. Printed copy (Folder 11)
  - "To Reduce the Cost of Eating", The Saturday Evening Post, 1921 March 5. Printed copy (Folder 12)
  - "The Decline of Prices of Cereals", Journal of Farm Economics, 1922 October. Reprint (Folder 13)
  - "The Future of the United States as a Food Exporter", Manchester Guardian Commercial Reconstruction in Europe, 1922 November 16. Reprint (Folder 14)
  - "The European Situation as Affecting the Demand for Wheat", speech, National Wheat Conference, Chicago, Illinois, 1923 June 19. Printed copy (Folder 15)
  - "Cooperative Production and Marketing", Sunset, Pacific Monthly, 1924 February. Reprint (Folder 16)
  - "The Food Needs of the Nation in Relation to Economic Resources", Journal of Home Economics, 1924 February. Reprint (Folder 17)
  - "The Future of Wheat Export from the United States", Quarterly Report of the Kansas State Board of Agriculture, 1924 March. Reprint (Folder 18)
  - "The Crux of the Wheat Problem", The Saturday Evening Post, 1924 March 29. Printed copy (Folder 19)
  - "Consumption, Merchandising, and Advertising of Foods", Harvard Business Review, 1924 April. Reprint (Folder 20)
  - "Disbursement of Family Income", Journal of Home Economics, 1925 September. Reprint (Folder 21)
  - "Empire Preference", The Saturday Evening Post, 1933 April 20. Printed copy (Folder 22)
  - "Retention, Restoration, and Fortification of Vitamins in Foodstuffs", Milbank Memorial Fund Quarterly, 1939 July. Reprint (Folder 23)
  - "Long-Term Effect of Under-and-Over-Nourishment", remarks, California Academy of Medicine, San Francisco, California, 1940 September 2. Printed copy (Folder 24)
  - Germany Then And Now, 1941. Printed copy (Folder 25)
  - "United Nations' Conference on Food and Agriculture", Scientific Monthly", 1943 November. Reprint (Box 2., Folder 1)
- FOOD ADMINISTRATION,1917-1926.
  Includes records of various departments of the United States Government, such as Council of National Defense, Export Administrative Board, State Department, War Industries Board and others. Also includes materials in French, German and Danish. See also OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - General (Folder 2)
  - Agreements (Folder 3)
  - Articles (Folder 4)
  - Charts and maps (Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. Includes letters to Herbert Hoover
    - Undated (Folder 7)
    - 1917
      - May-August (Folder 8)
      - September (Folder 9)
      - October (Folder 10)
      - November-December (Folder 11)
    - 1918
      - January-April (Folder 12)
      - May-December (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - 1919 (Folder 2)
    - 1920 (Folder 3)
  - Executive order (Folder 4)
  - Financial records (Folder 5)
  - Inventory (Folder 6)
  - Interview with Bolshevist representative in Romania (Folder 7)
  - Licensing records (Folder 8-14)
  - Memoranda
    - Bound volume, n.d. (Folder 15)
    - Loose
      - Undated (Folder 16)
      - 1917
        - May-August (Folder 17)
        - September (Folder 18)
        - October-December (Box 4., Folder 1)
      - 1918 (Folder 2)
      - 1919 (Folder 3)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - Undated (Folder 4)
    - 1917 August-November (Folder 5)
    - 1918
      - January-April (Folder 6)
      - May (Folder 7)
      - June (Folder 8)
      - July-August (Folder 9)
      - October-December (Folder 10)
    - 1919 May (Folder 11)
  - Newsletter (Folder 12)
  - Notes (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Printed matter (Folder 2)
  - Proposal (Folder 3)
  - Remarks
    - Undated (Folder 4)
    - 1917-1918 (Folder 5)
  - Reports
    - Undated (Folder 6)
    - 1916 (Folder 7)
    - 1917 (Folder 8)
    - 1918
      - January-May (Folder 9)
      - June-October (Folder 10)
      - November-December (Folder 11)
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 12)
  - Statements (Box 6.)
    - Undated (Folder 1)
    - 1917 (Folder 2)
    - 1926 (Folder 3)
  - Statistical data (Folder 4)
  - Subject file
    - Food
      - Allocations and deliveries (Folder 5)
      - Forecast report (Folder 6)
      - Lists of exports and imports (Folder 7-8)
      - Price charts (Box 7., Folder 1-3)
      - Production and consumption records (Folder 4)
      - Production and consumption records (Box 8., Folder 1-2)
      - Rationing system (Folder 3)
      - Requirements processed (Folder 4)
    - Statistical Department Information Service
      - Bulletins
        - 1917
          - July-November (Folder 5-9)
          - December (Box 9., Folder 1-2)
        - 1918
          - January (Folder 3-6)
          - February (Box 10., Folder 1-2)
          - March (Folder 3-4)
          - April (Box 11., Folder 1)
          - May (Folder 2-4)
          - June (Folder 5)
          - July-September (Box 12., Folder 1-3)
          - October-December (Folder 4-6)
        - 1919 January (Folder 7)
  - Telegrams (Box 13.)
    - Undated (Folder 1)
    - 1917-1920 (Folder 2-5)
  - Weekly bulletins
    - 1917 August-December (Folder 6)
    - 1918
      - February-October (Folder 7)
      - November-December (Folder 8)
    - 1919
      - January-February (Folder 9)
      - March-April (Folder 10)
      - May-June (Folder 11)
  - Writings by others (Folder 12)
- WAR TRADE BOARD, 1917-1919.
  Includes materials in Danish and French. See also FOOD ADMINISTRATION
  - General (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - Agreements (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Folder 3)
    - 1917 (Folder 4)
    - 1918
      - January-May (Folder 5)
      - June-November (Folder 6)
  - Memoranda
    - Undated (Folder 7)
    - 1917 (Folder 8)
    - 1918 (Folder 9)
    - 1919 (Folder 10)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - 1917 (Folder 11)
    - 1918
      - January-April (Folder 12-15)
      - May-August (Box 15., Folder 1-4)
      - September-December (Folder 5-8)
  - Notes (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - Organizational records (Folder 2)
  - Press release (Folder 3)
  - Printed matter (Folder 4)
  - Reports (Folder 5-6)
  - Statistical data (Folder 7)
  - Survey report (Folder 8)
  - Telegrams
    - Bound volumes
      - Cuba (Folder 9)
      - France (Box 17., Folder 1)
      - Great Britain (Folder 2-3)
      - Great Britain (Box 18., Folder 1)
      - Holland (Folder 2-3)
      - Holland (Box 19., Folder 1)
      - Italy (Folder 2)
      - Japan (Folder 3)
      - Mexico and South America (Folder 4)
      - Norway (Box 20., Folder 1)
      - Portugal-Italy-Greece-Liberia-Tunisia (Folder 2)
      - Spain (Folder 3-4)
      - Switzerland (Box 21., Folder 1)
    - Loose
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Denmark
        - 1917 (Folder 3)
        - 1918 (Folder 4-15)
      - France, 1918
        - June-August (Folder 16-18)
        - September-December (Box 22., Folder 1-4)
        - 1919 January-February (Folder 5)
      - Great Britain
        - 1917 (Folder 6)
        - 1918
          - January-April (Folder 7-10)
          - May-August (Box 23., Folder 1-4)
          - September-November (Box 24., Folder 1-4)
      - Russia, 1918 (Box 25.)
        - February-June (Folder 1-2)
        - September-December (Folder 3)
      - Sweden
        - 1917 (Folder 4)
        - 1918 January-December (Folder 5-16)
      - Switzerland, 1918 September-December (Folder 17-20)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1920.
  Applications, clippings, correspondence, economic condition, financial records, memoranda, notes, prison camp records and reports, and statistical data and weekly reports
  - World War, 1914-1918 - Civilian Relief, American - Europe (Box 26., Folder 1-4)
  - World War, 1914-1918 - Prisoners and prisons, German (Folder 5-14)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1911-1918.
  Article, clippings, correspondence, charts, conference proceedings, data sheets, maps, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes and telegrams relating to domestic production, exports and imports of food in the following countries
  - Denmark and the Netherlands (Box 27., Folder 1-2)
  - Norway and Switzerland (Box 28., Folder 1-2)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1921
  - 12 prints depicting American relief activities in Poland following World War I, American Feast in Warsaw, Polish children's kitchens and schools (album entitled "In grateful appreciation to Dr. Alonzo Taylor from the children of Poland", Warsaw, 1921) (Album Album fA)
  - 1 print depicting Alonzo E. Taylor, n.d. (Envelope Env. mB)